Guide to the Solis Horwitz Papers, 1945-1971 UA.90.F63
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Solis Horwitz Papers
1945-1971
1952-1967
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Horwitz, Solis
UA.90.F63
4.56 Linear Feet (2 records center and 3 oversize boxes)
This collection consists of scrapbooks, invitations, awards, and correspondence documenting Solis Horwitz's work within the federal government, 1945-1971. Horwitz was a University of Pittsburgh alumni and professor from 1968-1972.
Biography
The Honorable Solis Horwitz was born in 1910 and died in 1972. Horwitz earned both an A.B. (1930) and an A.M. (1932) from the University of Pittsburgh. He then went on to receive an LL.B. from Harvard Law School (1936) and started a private law practice in Pittsburgh the following year where he worked before joining the U.S Army in 1942. He served in the army until the end of World War II and then became Deputy Cheif Counsel of the International Prosecution Section, SCAP, for the trial of major war criminals before the International Tribunal for the Far East, Tokyo, 1945-1948.
Horwitz held many other positions over the next two decades including: Counsel, House Armed Services Committee for B-36 Investigation and Strategy and Unification Hearings, 1949; Council to the Chairman, National Security Resources Board, Executive Office of the President, 1950-1951; General Council, Reconstruction Finance Corporation, 1951-1953; Counsel to the Senate Committee on Government, 1954; Private practice, Pittsburgh and Washington, D.C., 1954-1957; Counsel to Senate Democratic Policy Committee, Senate Special Committee on Aeronautics and Space, and Preparedness Investigating Subcommittee of Senate Armed Services Committee for Missiles and Satellites Investigation, 1957-1960; Private practice, Washington, D.C., 1960; Director, Organizational and Management Planning, Office of the Secretary of Defense, 1961-1964; and Assistant Secretary of Defense for Administration, 1964-1968.
Horwitz resigned from the Department of Defense, where he had worked since the beginning of the Kennedy administration, in 1968 to take a position as professor at the University of Pittsburgh. He taught within several departments including Political Science, the Graduate School of Public and International Affairs (GSPIA), and the Law School. Horwitz was a professor at the University until his death in 1972. He taught Political Science 20: American Political Process, a Seminar in Decision Making in National Security, Modern Social Legislation, and a Seminar on the Separation of Powers. Please refer to the Biography (Box 1 Folder 1) folder for more detail on his government career.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection primarily focuses on Horwitz's professional activities in the United States Government, 1945-1968. Policies and reports, some classified at the time, are included and relate to his capacity as legal counselor and administrator at the Depart of Defense. Three extensive scrapbooks (Box 2-3) document both professional and personal events in his career in the government, 1961-1969, with 213 photos and numerous clippings. Also included are diplomas and certificates earned by Horwitz along with correspondence with government associates and presidential libraries.
Note: This collection is located on the oversized shelves
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was accessioned June 1999.
Previous Citation
Solis Horwitz Collection, 1945-1971, UA.90.F63, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989; University of Pittsburgh; Faculty papers; Reconstruction Finance Corporation; United States. Department of Defense; McCarthy, Joseph; Horwitz, Solis; Kaiser-Frazer Corp; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines); Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald)
- Biography (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence- General Government, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence- Transfer of oral history interview to J.F. Kennedy and L.B. Johnson Presidential Libraries, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence- Honorary degree from University of Pittsburgh, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence- University of Pittsburgh, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Reports and Addresses- General Government, prepared by Horwitz, 1953-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Reports and Addresses- General Government, 1952-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Reports and Addresses- Army-McCarthy Hearings, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Speech concerning Sputnik, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Reconstruction Finance Corporation- Correspondence, June 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Reconstruction Finance Corporation- Reports, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Reconstruction Finance Corporation- Loan Information and Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Reconstruction Finance Corporation- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Defense Department, general information and flow charts, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Defense report and defense publication, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Album of International Military Tribunal for the Far East, 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Award certificate from US Treasury Department, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Miscellaneous, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Scrapbooks, 1961-1969 (Box 2)
- Scrapbook, Photographs, Diplomas, 1952-1966 (Box 3)
- Law School Notebook- Bills and Notes (Box 4, Volume 1)
- Law School Notebook- Business Organizations (Box 4, Volume 2-3)
- Law School Notebook- Civil Procedures (Box 4, Volume 4)
- Law School Notebook- Conflicts (Box 4, Volume 5)
- Law School Notebook- Contracts (Box 4, Volume 6)
- Law School Notebook- Criminal Law (Box 4, Volume 7)
- Law School Notebook- Equity (Box 4, Volume 8)
- Law School Notebook- Evidence (Box 4, Volume 9)
- Law School Notebook- Federal Jurisdiction (Box 4, Volume 10)
- Law School Notebook- Jurisprudence (Box 4, Volume 11-12)
- Law School Notebook- Property (Box 4, Volume 13)
- Law School Notebook- Property (Box 5, Volume 1-2)
- Law School Notebook- Sales (Box 5, Volume 3)
- Law School Notebook- Taxation (Box 5, Volume 4)
- Law School Notebook- Torts (Box 5, Volume 5-6)
- Law School Notebook- Trusts (Box 5, Volume 7)
- Law School Notebook- Unidentified (Box 5, Volume 8)